Jacob Kainen
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Printed Material, 1939-2002, undated, Series 8:; (Boxes 13-14, OV 18; 0.4 linear feet)
  The series includes Kainen's exhibition catalogs and announcements in addition to newspaper, magazine, and journal clippings of articles by and about Jacob Kainen. The series also includes notecards and a list of items in Jacob's personal art collection and in Jacob and Ruth's joint art collection. A photocopy of the guestbook from Kainen's exhibition at the Equitable Gallery, a calendar, and two pamphlets produced by the Lab School of Washington are also included. The series is arranged alphabetically by type of material and chronologically under each heading.
  - Calendar, 1995 (Box 13)
  - Clippings of Articles about Jacob Kainen, 1952-2002, undated, (3 folders) (Box 13)
  - Clippings of Articles by Jacob Kainen (see also OV 18), 1956-1979, undated, (2 folders) (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings, 1952-1999, undated (Box 13)
  - Collection List, 2001, (3 folders) (Box 13)
  - Collection Notecards, undated, (6 folders) (Box 14)
  - Exhibition Catalogs and Announcements, 1938-1994, undated, (7 folders) (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous Announcements, 1939-1989, undated (Box 14)
  - Exhibition Guestbook, undated, (2 folders) (Box 14)
  - Pamphlets, undated (Box 14)
  - Clippings of Articles by Jacob Kainen, 1966 (Box 18 (OV))
- Photographs, 1905-2000, undated, Series 9:; (Boxes 14-16, OV 18; 2.6 linear feet)
  The series contains photographs of Jacob Kainen with family members and friends, at exhibition openings, and working in his studios. Included are color snapshots as well as black and white prints. There are a few negatives included within the series. Many of the photographs were taken by Ruth Cole Kainen. The series originally consisted of eight photograph albums and a box of loose photographs. The photograph albums were dismantled and the photographs within them were arranged in their original order. The albums were originally labeled with their dates. The dates have been preserved and the albums are organized chronologically by their dates. The loose photographs are organized alphabetically by subject and chronologically under each heading.
  - Dismantled Photograph Album, 1 of 8, 1905-1969, undated, (5 folders) (Box 14)
  - Dismantled Photograph Album, 2 of 8, 1969-1975, undated, (9 folders) (Box 14)
  - Dismantled Photograph Album, 3 of 8, 1975-1979, undated, (10 folders) (Box 14)
  - Dismantled Photograph Album, 4 of 8, 1979-1981, undated, (9 folders) (Box 14)
  - Dismantled Photograph Album, 5 of 8, 1981-1986, undated, (13 folders) (Box 15)
  - Dismantled Photograph Album, 6 of 8, 1985-1991, undated, (18 folders) (Box 15)
  - Dismantled Photograph Album, 7 of 8, 1989-1993, undated, (16 folders) (Box 15)
  - Dismantled Photograph Album, 7 of 8, 1989-1993, undated, (2 folders) (Box 16)
  - Dismantled Photograph Album, 8 of 8, 1994-1997, undated, (14 folders) (Box 16)
  - Exhibition Openings, 1973-1994, undated, (3 folders) (Box 16)
  - Jacob Kainen, 1925-1999, undated, (4 folders) (Box 16)
  - Jacob Kainen and Family (see also OV 18), 1905-1997, (3 folders) (Box 16)
  - Jacob Kainen and Friends, 1929-2000, undated (Box 16)
  - Jacob Kainen in the Studio (see also OV 18), 1972-2000, undated, (10 folders) (Box 16)
  - Ronald Reagan Washington National Airport, 1997, undated, (2 folders) (Box 16)
  - Works of Art by Jacob Kainen, 1991-1995, undated, (2 folders) (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous, 1979-1994, undated (Box 16)
  - Jacob Kainen and Family, undated (Box 18 (OV))
  - Jacob Kainen in the Studio, 1987 (Box 18 (OV))
- Works of Art by Others, 1944-2000, undated, Series 10:; (Boxes 16-17, OV 18; 1 linear foot)
  The series consists primarily of handmade greeting cards and limited edition prints given to Jacob and Ruth Kainen. The cards contain lithographs, etchings, pen and ink drawings, and woodblock prints by various artists such as Tadeusz Lapinski, Un-ichi Hiratsuka, and Raphael Soyer. Alberta Mayo's portfolio, entitled "Remembering Paradise: Postcards from Southern California," is also part of the series. The series contains a variety of materials given to Kainen by the artist, Irving Amen. The series is arranged alphabetically by the artist's last name and chronologically under each heading. Artists with fewer than five items are filed alphabetically in miscellaneous folders. The material by Irving Amen is organized further by the type of material (i.e. by works of art, photographs, and printed material) and then chronologically. See Appendix B for a complete list of the miscellaneous artists.
  - Unidentifiable and Illegible, (see also OV 18) 1968-2000, undated (Box 16)
  - Amen, Irving, 1960-1970, undated, (6 folders) (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous A: Arneson-Azechi, 1962, undated (Box 16)
  - Brumback, Cynthia and Wang Ming (see also OV 18), 1974-2000, undated, (4 folders) (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous B: Baskin-Butler, 1937-1990, undated (Box 17)
  - Childs, Bernard, 1968-1984 (Box 17)
  - Clark, Michael, 1977-1999, undated (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous C: Carcan-Cornin, 1959-1990, undated (Box 17)
  - Donovan, Bobby, 1987-2000, undated (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous D and E: Davis-Everson (see also OV 18), 1948-1987, undated (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous F and G: Fransconi-Gurr, 1971-2000, undated (Box 17)
  - Hiratsuka, Un-ichi, 1966-1977, undated, (2 folders) (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous H and I: Hashimoto-Isen, 1985-1991, undated (Box 17)
  - Jelinek, Hans, undated (Box 17)
  - Kainen, Dan, 1999-2000, undated, (4 folders) (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous K: Kent-Kurosuki, 1966-1979, undated (Box 17)
  - Lapinski, Tadeusz, 1969-1989, undated (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous L: Landau-Lyon, 1951-1979, undated (Box 17)
  - Mayo, Alberta, 1986, (3 folders) (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous M: Margo-Music, 1973-1978, undated (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous N: Nama-Neustadt, 1965-1971 (Box 17)
  - O'Connell, George (see also OV 18), 1962-2000, undated, (2 folders) (Box 17)
  - Oehser, Grace, 1953-1978 (Box 17)
  - Orbeck, Jay, 1979-1989, undated (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous P: Pearlstein-Purcell, 1977-1997 (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous R: Reed-Riabov, 1969-1971, undated (Box 17)
  - Schrag, Karl, 1960-1962, undated (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous S: Schwartz-Sundberg, 1944-1985, undated (Box 17)
  - Thorton, Valerie, 1967-1985, undated, (2 folders) (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous T and V: Taylor-Viswanadhan, 1962-1990 (Box 17)
  - Verejsky, Orest, 1965-1986, undated, (3 folders) (Box 17)
  - Wasserman, Burton, 1967-1972 (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous W and Y: Ward-Yunkers, 1948-1997, undated (Box 17)
  - Unidentifiable, 1980 (Box 18 (OV))
  - Brumbeck, Cynthia and Ming Wang, 1998-2000, (3 cards) (Box 18 (OV))
  - De Léon, Ponce, 1971 (Box 18 (OV))
  - O'Connell, George, undated (Box 18 (OV))
- Miscellany, 1999, Series 11:; (Box 17; 1 videocassette)
  The series consists of one videocassette about Martin Ries' paintings, prints, and drawings entitled, Live Along the Line: six decades.
  - Live Along the Line: six decades,1999 (Box 17)